**RT-Middleware Overview


**What is RT-Middleware? 
''RT-Middleware (RTM)'' is a ''software platform'' to construct the robot system (the RT system) by combining the software modules of the robot functional elements (the RT functional element).

An RT functional element is a robot component which provides a certain comprehensive function, which may be a device unit like Servomotor, Sensor, and Camera, or a combination of device units such as Mobile platform and Arm. Moreover, not only those connected with hardware but also those consisting only of software, such as control algorism or image processing algorithm, are also regarded as RT functional elements. 
As shown in the following figure, RT-Middleware is a platform to facilitate robot system configuration by combining modularized RT functional elements in a hierarchical order.

#br

#ref(rtsystem_integration_en.png,50%,center)
//#ref(RTCBasedServiceRobot.png,nolink,center)
CENTER:''Robot consisted of RT-Middleware and RT-Component''
#br

In the RT-Middleware, the software modularized components of RT functional element are called ''RT-Component (RTC)''. 
Each RT-Component has the interfaces, which called Port, to communicate with other components or exchange data.
The RT system is constructed by connecting the ports of multiple components as an aggregation of each RT-Component function.

In the system in the above figure, we will explain using an example of the conversational recognition component. It is assumed to have functions to recognize, observe user's voice and their expression and communicate with them by their sound or gesture etc, and it consists of the following sub components.

-Camera component 
-Stereovision component 
-Face recognition component 
-Microphone component 
-Speech recognition component 
-Conversational component 
-Head and arm component 
-Speech synthesis component

#br

#ref(rtcbased_hri_system_en.png,50%,center)
//#ref(RTCBasedSystemEx1.png,nolink,center)
CENTER:''Internal structure of the conversational recognition component''
#br

As shown in the above figure, the division component has the interface, called port, to communicate with other components, exchanges data and the command, and realizes one comprehensive function as a whole. 

**RT-Middleware Overview 
Middleware is generally defined like "it is software which locates between Os and the application program, and indicates a library or a program etc that offers the functions to improve convenience in a certain specific usage".

RT-Middleware is literally middleware for a robot system, and a series of software group provided as some libraries or programs.

RT-Middleware consists of:

-RT-Component framework
-RT-Middleware
-Basic RT-Component Group
-Libraries
-Basic Service Group
-Basic tool Group

RT-Middleware indicates the aggregation of these elements that are necessary to construct the robot system in the general meaning. 
In the narrow meaning, the software to manage and to control the RT-Components is indicated. 

***RT-Component Framework

RT-Component framework is a framework for creating the RT-Components.

When modularizing the components which constitute a robot system, modularization with various grading is considered. 

For example, units comprising devices, such as motor and a sensor, the complex systems, such as a mobile robot and an arm, and algorithm which carries out various processing can be mentioned, and system is built by integrating those in a hierarchical order.

In RT-Middleware, the essential software part of these RT functional elements is called ''Core logic''. 
''RT-Component framework'' is a structure for putting a skin called common interface to Core logic and treating these Modules systematically.

#br


#ref(RTCFrameWorkAndCoreLogic_en.png,50%,center)
CENTER:''RT-Component framework and Core logic''
#br

In an example of making a component from the algorithm of a stereovision as shown in the above figure, the program itself which implemented algorithm is equivalent to Core logic. 
By preparing RT-Component framework set with suitable ports and implementing stereovision algorithm in this framework, a stereovision component can be created.

The module which is implemented with Core logic by a component developer based on the component framework so as to be integrated into a system is called RT-Component.

An RT-Component framework hides the common interface and its behavior from a component developer or an integrator who builds a system by combining these components. 
Therefore, the component developer can concentrate on implementing the main logic, and the integrator can concentrate on the design of the whole system without thinking about the detail of the implementation.

***RT-Middleware 
In implementation, RT-Component forms a mere class or a shared library (In UNIX, it is Shared library. In Windows, it is Dynamic Link Library (DLL)). 
Since RT-Component does not have a main function as in C language or C++ language, it cannot execute as a program in itself. 
It is because RT-Component only defines processing (actions) executed according to the life cycle and condition.

The role of RT-Middleware is to execute the action defined by RT-Component. 
RT-Middleware (sometimes called a manager) generates instances of RT-Components, manages a lifecycle, executes the actions and mediates with various services, and so on. 
RT-Middleware is an execution environment, that is, a platform, for RT-Component.

***Basic RT-Component Group
RT-Component is a module which can be treated as a reusable component. If many RT-Components are generated and utilized mutually, even when building a new robot system, it can be easily built by reusing most of the existing components and generating only minimum of additional components. 
RT-Middleware includes fundamental and general-purpose RT-Components among such reusable RT-Components.

***Libraries 
RT-Middleware includes libraries used in common when programming software for a robot.

***Basic Service Group
When the robot system is constructed based on RT-Middleware, the part which isn't created as RT-Component, but provides a certain common function to the system is called service.
RT-Middleware includes these services.

***Basic Tool Group
The robot system configuration based on RT-Middleware can be divided into various phases, such as system design, component design, component development, system integration, and system execution. 

RT-Middleware includes various tools for helping a developer in such system-configuration processes. 

Since RT-Component has a common interface, most tools can be shared and the increase in efficiency of development can be expected.

**OpenRTM-aist
RT-Middleware and RT-Component are the terms to represent the above mentioned general concepts, and these are not limited to specific software.

OpenRTM-aist is a reference implementation of RT-Middleware that we, The National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology - Intelligent Systems Research Institute, have been implementing, distributing, maintaining.
RT-Components are designed and implemented using the distributed object middleware of CORBA based on network transparently, platform independence and language independence.
Currently, OpenRTM-aist provides the implementations for C++, Python and Java.

In RT-Middleware, there are OpenRTM.NET that is implemented for the .Net environment by Systems Engineering Consultants Co.,LTD, and OpenRTM Java that is implemented for Java by Mr.Hirano of National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology, Information Technology Research Institute.
It can be said that these implementations are also RT-Middleware, and these have interfaces of OpenRTM-aist-compatible at the same time, and these are kinds of OpenRTM because of the interoperable implementations of OpenRTM-aist.

***Structure of OpenRTM-aist
OpenRTM-aist consists of the following libraries and programs:

-RT-Component framework
-RT-Middleware
-Tools
--RtcTemplate
--RtcLink

Although the description of RT-Middleware given above mentioned that a basic component group, libraries, basic services etc are included in RT-Middleware in addition, these things are not yet included in the present OpenRTM-aist. 

We hope to apply OpenRTM-aist to various robot systems from now on and add these one by one.


***Procedure of Development Using OpenRTM-aist 
OpenRTM-aist consists of a framework for preparing the components and middleware for managing and executing the components.

A component developer generates RT-Components by integrating the existing logic which he developed into a component framework. 
A robot system is built by combining two or more components generated in this way.

The procedure of development using OpenRTM-aist is basically as follows:

+Define the specification of a component.
+Generate the templates of the component by using a cord generator.
+Integrate libraries etc. you have in a specific location in the template.
+Compile, test and debug.
+Integrate into a system.

As mentioned above, the processing for the common interface among RT-Components and the processing of data exchange with other components etc are hidden by the RT-Component framework. 
Since these processing are common, many parts can be made into a library and generated automatically. 
In OpenRTM-aist, RtcTemplate is provided as a basic tool for generating a template of this RT-Component.

***RT-Component Architecture
In OpenRTM-aist, RT-Components are defined as the following models of the components.

RT-Component consists of the following elements.

#br

#ref(RTCArchitecture_en.png,50%,center)
CENTER:''RT-Component Architecture''
#br

-''Component Profile'' : Meta information of a component. A series of information which show the characteristics of the component, such as the name of the component, and the profile of ports it has.
-''Activity'' : Core logic of a component. Activity has a state machine and Core logic is executed as processing (action) at the time of each state or the transition between states.
-''Execution Context'' : Abstract expression of a thread. It executes the activities according to the state.
-''Data Port'' : A port which supports data-oriented (Data Centric) communication. It abstracts transmission and reception of the components based on the Publisher/Subscriber model.
--''Data Input port (InPort)'' : A port to receive data from outside and to pass data to Core logic such as Activity etc. It has interface as Subscriber.
--''Data Output port (OutPort)'' : A port to send data generated by Activity to the outside. OutPort has Publisher in every connection, and passes data to InPort via the Publisher.
-''Service Port'' : A port which is able to have any service interfaces defined by users (the component developers). It is able to have any number and any kind of the interfaces.
--''Service Provider'' : An interface to provide service. Usually, it is created in order to provide access from outside, to the detailed function of Core logic of the component.
--''Service Consumer'' : An interface to use service. It is created in order to use other service providers of the component.
-''Configuration Interface'' : An interface to refer and modify the component parameters of Core logic externally. It can have several ConfigurationSets which include a list of pairs of parameter name and value, and an identifier name, and switch between its ConfigurationSets dynamically while running.


***RtcTemplate
RtcTemplate is a tool for generating the templates of the components from the component specification.

The component specification is meta information of RT-Component that consists of:

-Component Profile
--Component Name
--Category Name
--Version etc
-Data Port
--InPort and OutPort
--Port Name
--Data Type
-Service Port
--Port Name
--Service Interface
---Interface Name
---Provider Consumer

and if such information is the same, the appearance looks exactly the same from the system even when implementation of RT-Components differs. 
Moreover, if the specification of the component other than the property is the same and has the same behavior, those RT-Components can be exchanged.

For example, suppose that two cameras were created into the components. 

One was created as a component handling a USB camera on Windows, and another was a component which video capture device on Linux was created. 
If these components have the same Data port, Service port etc, since these two camera components regard as the same from other components using these, the two can be mutually exchanged.

In development with C++, the entity of RT-Component is a class which inherited the base class of RT-Component. 
RtcTemplate embeds Data ports, Service ports, variables for Configuration information and initialization functions in this class. 
A component developer only needs to write codes for retrieving and writing out data from data ports, implementation and utilization of services, and utilization of Configuration information.

For example, it reads data from data input port (InPort) like this;

 // m_inport is the instance of InPort.
 m_inport.read();
 // m_inval is data variable related with InPort.
 use_data_from_inport_func(m_inval.data);

you can receive and use the sent data of other components by only this operation.

It writes data to data output port (OutPort) like this;

 // m_outval is data variable related with OutPort
 m_outval = set_data_for_outport_func();
 // m_outport is the instance of OutPort
 m_outport.write();

you can send the data to other components by only this operation.

***RtcLink 
RtcLink is a GUI tool which provides a basic operation environment required in order to build a system by combining multiple RT-Components. 
It enables to acquire the meta information of RT-Components and read the profile of the components and of Data port and Service port which the component has. 
Moreover, it provides a graphical environment for connecting data ports and service ports by drag-and-drop with a mouse. 
Thus, a system built with multiple RT-Components can be started up and operated as one system.

Since OpenRTM-aist is built with distributed objects, RT-Components distributed to multiple Nodes (PC or embedded computer etc) on the network can be handled transparently. 
For example, it is possible to build a simple remote control system by connecting the component of an arm which is operating by Node A to the Joystick component which is operating by Node B, or it is also possible to remake into an automatic control system of the arm by connecting with an autonomous control component which is operating by Node C instead of the joystick component.

In addition, if RtcLink is used, switching of such connection can also be performed dynamically while keeping the components running. 
RtcLink can also control the whole system from another computer different from these Nodes due to the network transparently by the distributed objects.
